Today, there are around 12,000 nuclear
warheads somewhere on Earth. That's
12,000. 12,000. That's enough firepower
to level every sizeable city on the
planet several times over.
The world used to have way more, like
more than triple that during the Cold
War. Almost every one of these nuclear
warheads today
is in the hands of two countries, the US
and Russia.
But in total, there are nine countries
that possess these destructive bombs.
And one of these countries doesn't admit
that they have nuclear weapons, but they
do.
And America's nukes aren't just in
America. They're scattered all over the
world, in allied countries, on land, in
air, deep in the ocean, lurking in
submarines, in a configuration that the
US calls its nuclear posture. It's one
of the most important parts of America's
military strategy today. And we're about
to see how it actually works in real
life. Because these 12,000 nukes shape
our entire world. Their threat is
ever-present. And so it turns the
chessboard of geopolitics into a
different thing than it was before. So
the central idea of all of this is
pretty simple, pretty intuitive, kind
of. But then it kind of messes with your
brain in weird ways, and we'll see how
that works.
You've got these two big empires.
They're rivals. They're competing with
each other as big countries do and have
always done, and maybe someday they
won't, but they do for now. If there's
no nukes in this equation, history has
taught us that these two big empires
will fight each other over land, over
influence, over resources, over honor,
over who knows. They will fight each
other. That always has happened. Like
that is the central threat of humanity
is big powerful entities will fight each
other. In recent centuries, it's gotten
really destructive. Like think of Europe
and Asia in the 1940s. Countries are
fighting because there's a chance that
one of them can win. Okay. Now, after
1945, put nukes on the board and watch
what happens. This new weapon that could
inflict damage of the kind that we just
never before imagined in human history.
Now, if these two empires get into a war
with each other, they both know that it
will escalate. They will keep using more
and more extreme force until eventually
one side will use nukes.
To which the other will respond with
their own nukes. And then it's game over
for everyone. Nobody wins. Everybody
loses. The world is on fire. The concept
of victory becomes irrelevant because
everyone's dead. This creates a calculus
of fear, an understanding that you will
inflict way more consequences on
yourself if you go to war with your
geopolitical rival. And this threat of
total destruction is stronger than the
urge to fight and dominate. After World
War II, after we witnessed this
destructive bomb in Hiroshima and
Nagasaki, something changed. We crossed
a line of understanding that there
really was something that could really
sort of end it all.